[SPEAKER_00]: Do you have something particular in mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not specifically.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had kind of the idea of something similar we've done with Tanya, three of us, when I... after we recorded samatha and vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the thing I had in mind is...
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to ask you about the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the body?
[SPEAKER_00]: So... A lump of flesh and bone.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sitting here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that how you see it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Right now, I'm kind of... Yeah, it's this kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from your point of view... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the only point of view you can have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eh... Abstaining from assuming the external.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have these ideas of it being matter, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: I have those ideas of It being matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the It of It, without resorting to the external ideas of what It is?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the It?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's this thing that was like... that makes it all of this possible for me to be sitting here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Talk to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perceiving all this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hearing all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's another secondary idea to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you don't see that possibility when you look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, but I do... You learn that about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I do think of it as, like, the extent that of my experience that make, you know, that the kind of... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, as I said, once you think about it... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, having thought about it, that's what I've sort of... those are the ideas I have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having not thought about it in terms of all the relevant ideas that pertain to it, when I ask you, it, the body, what is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you referring to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it felt?
[SPEAKER_01]: Perceived?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are its characteristics of the it aspect of the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the ideas and aspect that you have about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's perceived in various ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the body right here, right now, that you have while you're talking to me, is perceived in various ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: What ways?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, well, I can see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can see there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't tend to normally look down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you close your eyes, is it still there?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, sorry, as the body, yes, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, what is that one?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's independent of your sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the kind of... let's say, the center of the perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go on.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the characteristics of...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... it's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not... that's not so relevant now, I was thinking, but sometimes it's like... it's to do with...
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason why I would reach over there and make a coffee is because the body is made that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, to have a drink and to...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, usage of the body is separate to the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but it's fully determined by that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's fully made up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is the way it is because that's the way the body is.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the way it is?
[SPEAKER_00]: The way I'm acting is just bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's secondary to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way you can act is the ways that are possibly outlined by the possibilities of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, okay, that's also...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a characteristic, but it's secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: What would be the primary characteristics of it, the way it is right here, right now, in your presently enduring experience?
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess, well... Like, whatever ambiguous terminology you might end up using, doesn't matter, use it, as long as you sort of approximate to what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was thinking then of something that's alive, something that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just in case, I don't know, but don't try to figure it out, but more like just try to keep your mind on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I was trying to see what comes out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm trying to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm trying to then say something about, like, just this being alarmed.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the most obvious characteristic that would first pop to your mind if you're like it, like my body right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I have the secondary thoughts about it, I have the memories of the visual images of my body from my point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, all of that refers to something, and that something, that thing, that it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is a container?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a kind of container.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you describe a container, supposedly?
[SPEAKER_01]: But, just in itself, not the purpose, not the possibilities, just in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, stuff, matter, that's an aspect of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's an aspect of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is there a feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you imagine the container, it, the body, presently and duly there, or whatever it is, without also there being a feeling present?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, that's the only reason why I know there's this container there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because of those, these perceptions and feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I was originally talking about perceived perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, all that can be discerned on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm asking you about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like, you go into perceptions and they become explanations.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know how it's to be rooted in the right things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point here is, I want you...
[SPEAKER_01]: I want your mind to remain rooted on the experience of it is, to the extent that it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it being the body, in this case.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can use that contemplation in regard to anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling, mind, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now we're doing about the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you touched upon matter, relate to matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you describe them all?
[SPEAKER_00]: Present, enduring body, material...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just like a lump, or it's like... it's a...
[SPEAKER_00]: Something that resists me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something that resists.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, would you say that matter resists you to that extent?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that the matter that resists you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems to be the closest bit of matter that resists me.
[SPEAKER_01]: The closest bit of matter that resists you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the most important?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The most.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The closest, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying the closest bit of matter that resists you implies further bits of matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because... What are the further bits of matter?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I can, you know, I like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm stuck in this room or I'm supported by this chair.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all kind of resistance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that seems to be... that seems to be only... it seems to be secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's... because it's experienced via this bit of matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, furthermore, is it that you experience the secondary matter through this matter?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you know that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Since already your experience of your body is already a secondary experience of the matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the body against the chair.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just this feeling of...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you said that the body is basically the... how did you put it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a matter that exists to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first matter that exists to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the only matter that exists to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot possibly know any other matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it, the body, the lump of flesh, whichever way you described it, whichever way you designated it, is presently enduring right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that material aspect, to the extent that it's material,
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there any other accessible or experienced matter outside of that aspect that you can even...?
[SPEAKER_00]: Experienced matter outside...?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you experience the matter apart from your body?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have perceptions of... and then you can secondarily assume that that's because there's matter there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assume?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, does that mean, like, if you stop assuming that there is a matter there, those things would cease to be material?
[SPEAKER_01]: What would happen then?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it doesn't need that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't need...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, your perceptions would basically stop assuming matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, as the Buddha said, the perception would stop conceiving the matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no, like, the real matter you need to figure out.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to stop mistaking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the level of your perception, Mūla Pāryāya Sutta starts, he perceives
[SPEAKER_01]: Having perceived the earth, he conceives in earth, from earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the perception... and then the... the seka and the arahant, he directly knows, he understands.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize that the perception of kutujana, that's already what his ignorance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's another idea that people who know that they don't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: A person knows he's not a sotāpanna, but thinks that he can practice the dhamma by observing his perceptions, by perceiving things purely.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you heard it millions of times in dhamma talks and whatnot, the pure awareness, the pure perception, the purity of the present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is already... your purity is already ignorant.
[SPEAKER_01]: The perception already misconceives or conceives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any form of conceiving is misconceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the lack of the clarity of that, that's how you perpetuate the mistake of conceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whatever else you build up on top of that misconceived perception, it cannot be right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why Mūla Paryāsutta goes to the point of saying, he perceives nibbāna as nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because... because he perceives it, as in, ignorantly, he conceives in it, apart from it, he conceives nibbāna's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He implies himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter what you perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's another thing when people are perceiving and observing their sensations, their movements, body portions.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all based... on the basis of perceiving, perceiving, perceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Expecting the reality to come as a result of it, failing to see that it's the actual perceiving that's the problem, not what you're perceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're perceiving that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Perceiving always would imply... would imply... it's always... it's always taken for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will have to be, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not seeing perceiving to be fully within the container of present, enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience as a whole, the body, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, the only way you can designate it is, as in the body is, is also to perceive it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that you realize.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where your whole practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop misconceiving it through your perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, learn how to perceive it on its own terms, not on the terms of your own conceiving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the purification the Buddha talks about.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that will require, then, to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding of the it, in the nature, the characteristics of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The characteristic of this it, that will help uncut that perception, is the fact that it is just, is given, is like, is...
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize the only reason you're conceiving things... thrown at me.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're conceiving things through a perception, is through not understanding that, that you're conceiving makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Matter is there, mattering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception is there, perceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings are there, feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not fully understanding that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the whole notion of conceiving, which means I am, mine, for me, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's completely gratuitous, that entire thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to do like the mindfulness of the body, meditation or contemplation,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clarifying what the phenomenon of presently enduring it is, the body, is, for me, without misconceiving it through my carelessly attending to it, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Careless attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not looking closely enough and then just building my practice on top of whatever I took for granted, which is the way I perceive things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it will just perpetuate the wrong views further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the presently enduring this body, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you be aware of this presently enduring body right here, right now, in the past or in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always where your present is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you leave it for a while and then come back to it, as in you really leave the container of that body, the necessity of it for its experience, so you can't escape it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inescapable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's ines...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, any past that you remember, any future that you plan, where is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all in this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's within this it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is there then any need for you to come back to the body, to the present moment?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, because you already are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you couldn't have left in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you practicing returning back to the present moment, which is another relatively common practice, maintains your view that you can leave the present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you left the present moment when you be... when you started ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It implies that you can step into the outside, even if you blame it for your distraction, you still assume that it is possible to go that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you're inside or outside, past, future, present, far, near, big or small, as the Buddha would describe it, the body is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why satipaṭṭhāna is understanding body, mindfulness of the body to the extent necessary for final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, develop that mindfulness, because that's what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: An enduring phenomenon of mind established upon the body, regardless of the past, regardless of the future, regardless of the present actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding that it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot replace it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only... what you can only do is ignore it, and by doing so, you become the owner of it, through misconceiving it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can stop ignoring it, and by doing so, you stop misconceiving it, and you remove your ownership, because you realize it's impossible to own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, that presently enduring it, is the basis, the container, whatever you want to call it, of any conceivable, even utter, abstract, imaginative experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any...
[SPEAKER_01]: But a question that comes up now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is the body, that body that you're describing, that's presently enduring, is that the matter?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, how does it then resisting it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: How?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that image was
[SPEAKER_00]: Trust upon me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't ask for that image.
[SPEAKER_01]: That image of the body is trust upon you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is that image?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's under the sofa.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, if you want to say where, it's like... Where's the image?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, where is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where would you place it?
[SPEAKER_00]: I wouldn't place it anywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Asking where is it, where is it, implies that it's in somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole notion of space is the result of that present enduring container.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's that's the whole the division between here and yonder, as in the sense of sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, things are already there enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: All notions of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is comes after.
[SPEAKER_01]: Secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, dwelling on that will basically prevent you from placing it gratuitously in space, outside of me, inside of me, neither here nor there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: He stops assuming it here, yonder, or in between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, both and neither.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's free from conceiving in every regard.
[SPEAKER_00]: And any, any, any notion of, kind of, expectancy?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, kind of, waiting or hoping or... For a result or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything like that always involves an image of something outside of this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, given the practically,
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot even conceive outside, as in fundamentally, but practically, you maintain the view of expectation of something from outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize you directly conceived outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're solely responsible for the existence of the notion of outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: And unless you address that, absolutely no amount of your effort can result in the right practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what the right practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Undoing the conceivings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Undoing the wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the presently, then, enduring body is then material and mental at the same time, depending on how you look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, there is an image, which is... it's already a phenomenon, it's already an image, it's already a form of thought, but it wouldn't be there if it weren't dependent on matter as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, your only relationship
[SPEAKER_01]: Your first port of call, in the experience of the body as a whole, right this body here, is a present enduring image that's kind of rooted in something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, that's where your conceivings come in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to repossess what, what, where it is rooted in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that gives you the sense of ownership and control.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't matter how much you try to reach, where it is rooted, as in the material side of the present enduring body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how far you try and reach, it's always a step below you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always determined as a step away from your effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable to be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm going to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Travelling the universe will never reach the end of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, the only way to repossess
[SPEAKER_01]: The necessary basis for this present in-duty body, thus becoming the owner of it, is to pretend that you reached that because of which the body is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's to conceal it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, this is the matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that I'm actually secondarily only can access, not even access, but relate to through the body, I assume it's that because of which this body is here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And look, I own this, thus I own this body, thus I am my own master in control of my experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why
[SPEAKER_01]: Sickness, aging and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: The most uprooting, basically, contemplations you can have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That make you realize that... Because it's not uprooting this body or that body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not uprooting the image of the body that you have of yourself in the mirror or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's uprooting this currently perceived and felt lump of
[SPEAKER_01]: the universe that you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot conceive outside of it, so it's only your relationship within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the body is, and that's what is subjected to destruction and change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is that present enduring body still there?
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't imagine it not being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... what are... do any other characteristics come to your mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, just, not theoretically, presently, enduring... You have the body, whether you're talking, whether you're listening, what I'm saying, whether you're replying, there is the body enduring there.
[SPEAKER_01]: What image, as in, what are the characteristics now of that which you established is a mental material image?
[SPEAKER_00]: The characteristics of that image, that I'm kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like I said before, like, I'm subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Entirely, utterly, completely, which means...
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't create, I didn't design this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just... all I do when I talk to you about it is describe something that's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, so, within that, that image that you said, it resists you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The manifestation of that resistance means, basically, a degree of independence... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...towards you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indifference.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I could just die any minute.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't care.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's completely unaware of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you were to, say, develop that context of the necessary basis of your experience of any conceivable kind... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...doesn't even know about your existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't exist for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would that be a true statement?
[SPEAKER_01]: To say that the basis of this presently enduring Lama flesh, which is mental material, basically... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...it's a phenomenon enduring the dhamma,
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't even know about my attempted ownership and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's impenetrable by me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able then, if that statement is true, which obviously it is, even, you know, after a little bit of thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you then, or rather, not would you, but more like, so why are you still then subjected to passion,
[SPEAKER_01]: Lust, aversion, desire for distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess because that context hasn't been established clearly enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: What context?
[SPEAKER_00]: What you just described, of this, this...
[SPEAKER_01]: But why, why would you need to, why would you need to establish it, when you said it's already there, and you have no choice but have it there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but it's... What is it exactly that you're establishing then?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, I find that when I... that recognizing that, that image, that context, is like recognizing something that's already there, but that I don't always remember, I don't always
[SPEAKER_01]: But as we described before, whether you get distracted by your past, future, whatever else, you can't actually be distracted from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how is then your forgetting of it...
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignoring.
[SPEAKER_01]: How is then your ignoring preventing you from understanding it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that seems... Why is your ignoring a factor?
[SPEAKER_00]: That seems to be what ignoring does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring, then, the de facto response, if you're ignoring, is to assume ownership over something, which you've just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Which you can't own.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is that ownership, then, if you can't own it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely confused.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is it then still there?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a good question.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's impossible to step outside of the presently enduring moment of the presently enduring mental material image of the body...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's obviously an element of wanting to own it, because there's a pleasure in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It don't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanting to own it makes no difference to the body that's unaware of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, wanting to own it, not wanting to own it, accepting it, rejecting it, acting out of it, makes absolutely no difference to the matter, to the form, to... Because it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is it still there?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's my question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it still there?
[SPEAKER_00]: All I can say is just by... because of not having accepted that, the nature of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not having seen it sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not having seen it long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or as the Buddha said, not having seen it to the extent necessary for final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, you haven't been seeing it long enough, literally,
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's impossible to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by virtue of that, that's why you're ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, the question is, so, why are you then not seeing it sufficiently enough?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or in other words, since distraction can't take you away from the necessary base of your experience for distraction, or non-distraction, or whatever you choose to do,
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you go about seeing it to the extent necessary?
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the body to the extent necessary for final knowledge of removing all dispassion towards it?
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess it's like dwelling, reminding, reminding myself about that, about the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, the reminding of yourself, why would you be doing that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it implies that you can't forget.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you forget?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There obviously is a forgetting involved in not seeing it for long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the characteristics of forgetting?
[SPEAKER_00]: Generally?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, specifically.
[SPEAKER_01]: What constitutes loss of mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mindfulness is present in the enduring body, that's there, whether you think of it or not, whether past, future, whatever memories you have, it's there primarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot conceive experience outside of it or independent of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Given that it's unforgettable, how can you forget about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: By assuming that you can forget about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how do you do that practically?
[SPEAKER_00]: How does that make sense practically?
[SPEAKER_00]: By just ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By just not looking at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By... by... Well, again, not looking at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you cannot truly not look at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, no, you cannot look at it in the sense that you can choose to ignore the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, I choose to ignore this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means it's still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't really ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you attempting at ignoring.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that involved?
[SPEAKER_01]: What does that involve?
[SPEAKER_01]: Doing something that you can't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that implies that you're doing something you can't actually do, yet you commit to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: To do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the necessary basis for that type of commitment, of ignoring the unignorable?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, more practically, more practically.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is a common ground to whenever you choose to ignore or engage with something, although you know you can't own it, you can't have it, yet you do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: A lack of authenticity, lack of faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, again, that's on the level of the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Practically, like, say, you want to distract yourself now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Remember, whenever you decided to distract yourself, why did you distract yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: What was the reason for that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that, oh, because I'm inauthentic... No, none of those can be your motivations.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's... What is pleasant?
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you see it as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it's always, basically, a matter of choice upon how you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why forgetfulness is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Genuinely forgetting things, it's within present enduring mindfulness of the of the mental material body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the choice you make within that, which means you're fully aware of it, that is rooted in how you feel, which is basically a choice rooted in desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the common ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire for more, desire for less, desire for neither.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha didn't say like, oh, you don't forget every moment of your life, watch every second of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just said, avoid unwholesome and cultivate wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't choose anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: rooted in greed, aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it will result in what?
[SPEAKER_01]: It will result in you ceasing to maintain gratuitous notion of ignoring that which is unignorable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, once you fully develop that, you cannot ignore it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the process of uprooting ignorance is utterly, completely irreversible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot then start ignoring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because what you thought ignoring was, as in, when you just forget, or you decided something, you're doing something else, you can't think of everything to the same extent at all times.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you thought that that was the reason for your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wasn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: The desire is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is always conscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can never accidentally stumble upon decisions rooted in desire, actions that you perform on account of desire, whether for more, for less, aversion, delusion, distraction, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why... the reason why I'm coming back to this is because that's pretty much like a... one of the main stumbling blocks for whoever starts, or even like later to develop it, is assuming that you must be in this... like maintain this clarity of this is unownable, this is unownable, this is unownable every second of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which kind of implies that you can still lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't lose it when you don't think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't lose it when you go to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't lose it when you choose to do something of... that's not rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when people don't know where the problem is, then they blame everything to be the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mustn't do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Isn't that craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Isn't that a desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to go for... well, that's craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well, that's attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: What craving is, what desire is, what attachment is, whatever you want to call it, is when you decide to act upon desire, upon aversion, or upon need for distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you choose to act on account of how you feel, in regard to how you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you feel pleasantly, you want to protect it,
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't have more of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You choose to act.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, having thoughts of protecting it is not on the same level as choosing to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you maintain this completely gratuitously, wrongly assumed order that we just described, that it's actually unassumable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you maintain your gratuitous ownership as well, of things that you know are unownable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, your ownership is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you still don't know what the basis for that ownership is, and you're scalelessly maintaining the base of the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if you look at the base of the ownership, you'll say, ah, it's... it's not having enough mindfulness, it's distraction, it's this, it's this, it's this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that is fully understood, to the point of, like as I said, distraction is not forgetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Distraction is basically choosing to distract yourself through the means of desire, through the means of aversion, through the means of distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what distraction is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're about to do something, oh, I must stop doing, no?
[SPEAKER_01]: I must know where it is rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how I will stop maintaining the basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't stop doing things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's another doing, which is not doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, am I doing this in order to... because of a particular feeling in regard to how I'm feeling right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, if you're acting out of how you're feeling, based on that lack of context, you will be acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are, sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're acting on the basis of how you're feeling, you will be acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're acting... as I said, like, see, people are not even aware of most... many of the actions, because you're only aware of the ones that are based on your desire or things you want, you know, but you do millions of things in the meantime.
[SPEAKER_01]: You open the door, you close the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those are little choices which you make.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are kind of neither wholesome or unwholesome, which means they are not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you can do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to get paralyzed about what do I do, what do I do then, what do I do, because all the doing is the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Specific type of doing, doing that's rooted in desire, doing that's rooted in craving in regard to how you're presently feeling while you're doing it, those are the ones you shouldn't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let those... when the monks tried... some monks tried to make him make those austere practices mandatory for everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody should say no to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody should say...
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let those who want to say no to such and such life, say no to that, to like living under... living in the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, roof dwellings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let those who want to eat one meal a day, eat one meal a day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let those who want to wear hand robes, wear hand robes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those who don't want to, not to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whatever... what specifically you're doing, only goes so far.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you specifically must abstain from... from sensual indulgence, chasing sense... sense pleasures, sexual intercourse and all these other things, if you want full enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't mean, like, you remain like a motionless log for the rest of your life, until you become an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it means that you just don't do things that are rooted in desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's another... the simile of the... the bait, the herd, the herd sutta in the Majjhima.
[SPEAKER_01]: The bait, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The bait about the deer herd.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first one just takes everything, the second one rejects everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the wise one is the one that realizes, you know, so you have to eat, as in you have to act, you have to remain engaged to some extent, in terms of breathing, walking, sitting, lying down.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those are choices you make.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only the choices that are rooted in desire, which is basically craving in regard to how you feel, that's what you don't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why Mahārāja will be unable to see you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you will become free.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you stopped eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: You removed all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's attachment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And no one will see the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And externally, nobody can measure you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Including devas and brāhmaṇas can't measure you, because you don't manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let alone Putrajana will be able to see you and pay you respects.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are no criteria for what enlightenment is.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can he possibly know?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's so important, because unless you clarify this, the characteristics of the present enduring body right here, right now, even when you forget, when you remember, you realize this is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is a necessary basis for any experience, including experience of forgetting, including the experience of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about uprooting and finding this universal kind of hidden truth that holds the whole set up on its palm, and now you got it all, basically, because you transcended everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's what you were given, stop misconceiving it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you stop misconceiving it when you fully understood that it's impossible to misconceive it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, whether you conceive it or not, it makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things are like this, to this extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the law of impermanence and these things, the universal principles.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you say, okay, so how do I stop misconceiving it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, by not being forgetful and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but why is forgetfulness the problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why did I do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because of the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I guess people...
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess the tendency is to kind of... when you suddenly become mindful, let's say, you might go, oh, yes, I've not been mindful for a while.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must be mindful from now on, rather than... rather than recognizing that, hang on a minute, I'm mindful of something now that cannot have been there even while I wasn't being mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of you, when you become mindful,
[SPEAKER_01]: Developing the view that that's what mindfulness is, and you have to develop more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead, don't take their view and start questioning further that which you discovered through your first attempt at mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when a person has a first attempt at mindfulness, they have a set of how it's felt, how it's perceived, what are its characteristics, and they take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, the whole point is to not take and keep going inwardly, as in digging inwardly further and further, not like, oh, no, now I know what mindfulness is, now I just need to develop this mindfulness that I know what it is, to the extent necessary to be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, the extent necessary means the extent necessary of understanding it to the necessary extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the mindfulness is about...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's like... Yeah, for most people, they think, like, even Puthujana knows what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just when you're present.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he's recognizing a phenomenon, but you have to understand what that phenomenon is, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're properly mindful once you understand what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you develop that understanding to the extent necessary, that's how all the unwholesome things will fall off.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or can you say, you're only mindful of the body when you understand what the body is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness is the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on you doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding of the necessary base for experience is what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the four foundations of mindfulness, basically understanding the four foundations of your experience, is the four foundations of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point I'm making, is people think they can do mindfulness, do meditation technique, do their observance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only reason they can do it is because their view conceives them as doable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they'll never approve their wrong view for as long as they do it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, fully understanding the necessary basis of your experience, the present in yours, whether you ignore it or not, makes your mindfulness impeccable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever comes...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness, the Buddha said, mindfulness is properly developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, things of extreme nature will not be able to perturb it, because, again, it doesn't matter how extreme.
[SPEAKER_01]: Big, small, far, near, heavy, light.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever your experience is, this is presently, during, there is a necessary basis for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The lamp of body, which is your universe, which is your whole container, which is like... has nothing...
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no relationship of... that you can
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't conceive on the same footing as it is, as that body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything you can conceive, it's the words, against, before, after, it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But nothing on the level of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why even you can't put it in space and say it's in my head or it's in...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do assume that, means you're not seeing its nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any movement in regard to it will be secondary and that was never a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that your mind must stop moving, because that will become your movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, stop misconceiving that which is inconceivable, or stop conceiving the inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is inconceivable?
[SPEAKER_01]: Form is inconceivable, feeling is inconceivable, perception is inconceivable, your intentions are inconceivable, consciousness is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable means you have removed your misconceivings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when people are inconceivable, they fail to see that that becomes their new conceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't think the inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only stop conceiving it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you stop conceiving it not by developing pure awareness of the presently enduring magical moment of your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You basically stop conceiving it through acting out of desire,
[SPEAKER_01]: Acting out of craving, acting out of intentional choice or ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's doable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, when will enlightenment happen to me?
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been doing it for twenty...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you've been doing it for twenty years, and you don't even have the right view, you're obviously doing it wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because as the Buddha said, it's impossible, if somebody's doing these things rightly, for the results to not take place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if a hen sits on her eggs, even if she doesn't wish, may my chicks pierce out of the shell safely, they will, because she sits on them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if a hen thinks she's sitting on her eggs, but no chicks are piercing out, maybe she should reevaluate what constitutes sitting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe I'm sitting in the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, it is like, again, like, what is the purpose of your practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Of any form of commitment to the dhamma as a lay person or as a monk, okay, you want to achieve something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: How are you going about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's, oh, I want to achieve, so I have no lack of clarity of what I want, further lack of clarity of how I'm going about it, and yet, here I am, fully committed to my meditation retreat and practice and just have expect things to occur to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And measure, basically, success by the experience of pleasure I get from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is the it-body, did we start describing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Furthermore, have its characteristics changed?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another reason why people mistake it into
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it always remains the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start assuming it's unchangeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or invisible.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just... Oh, you stop seeing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's actually, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's even more so, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're still subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still that... a certain... opaque lamp that resists you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: That my whole life.
[SPEAKER_00]: My everything depends on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's still an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you cannot even think anything...
[SPEAKER_01]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't even finish that sentence without finding an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you know that body if there is no image of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the only means.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only means are means that are already materially mental or mentally material.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's nāmarūpa, basically, is the definition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if there is no nāma of it, if there is no designated aspect of the present enduring lamp, it's inconceivable, as in, it's not manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't, whether you conceive it or stop conceiving it, you can't do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is nothing to be designated, that's when people say, ah, it's all in your head, it's all in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all in your mind, or it's all in the world, are already on the level of your mind, which is mentally material.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is something you are subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, therefore, there is that resistance aspect to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you had no say in how that image manifests.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only discern its given characteristics.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you truly were responsible for concocting it with your designation, with your naming, as people sometimes try to blame the naming for the issue,
[SPEAKER_01]: You would then be responsible for the creation of its characteristics, which wouldn't be its characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: There would be no it to designate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even like an artist, if they draw some paint or something, if you ask them where did it come from, they say, oh, I just drew
[SPEAKER_00]: That thing that... Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm secondary, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't really create it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's the thing, like, as I said, all of the five aggregates are indifferent to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your feelings, your own intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to... the way we examine the nature present during body, take up... it's slightly subtler to examine, so I usually just stick to the body, because people might be hearing this, so I just get... it's already hard enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you do develop skills, you can do the same examination, the same type of reflection and contemplation in regard to your presently doing intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you have intention to do something, what is the... what are the characteristics of the image that's necessarily contained for your intention?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the intention?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You chose to attend it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only choose to attend that which is given.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the whole thing can be boiled down, as the Buddha said, to correctly attending things or incorrectly attending things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not correctly manifesting and creating and fabricating or incorrectly.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that which is given on its own, that which arises, manifests, which endures on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have a choice to attend properly or improperly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Improper attention results in increasing of sensuality and decreasing of non-sensuality, increasing of hate and decreasing of non-hate, increasing of ignorance and decreasing of non-ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Proper attention results in opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Decreasing of sensuality and increasing of non-sensuality, decreasing of hate and increasing of non-hate, and decreasing of ignorance and increasing of non-ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you want it or not, it's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is up to you, is what you choose to attend to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things rooted in desire, or things rooted in non-desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: Things rooted in trying to change how you feel, or things rooted in not trying to change how you feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only reason that
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is still not free from gratuitous conceivings that are actually impossible to conceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is... because of the choices you make.
[SPEAKER_01]: And is... is there anybody, anywhere in the universe, in the past, or in the future, other than you, that can be responsible for those choices?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another inconceivable thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable that anybody else can be owner of your kāma, which is a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not a mystical energy, just in case people are not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's inconceivable that... and that's what it's meant by.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are the sole owner of your choices and the results of those choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: The result being mind still not being free.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a direct result of the choices that still entertain the extent
[SPEAKER_01]: The extent of desire, the extent of aversion, the extent of distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if a question is posed, why are you not an arahant yet?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you're preventing yourself from being one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, also, it's my fault then.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to regard it as a fault, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how you label it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is, you're responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it will be impossible to not become an arahant, if you stop making choices, stop acting out of choices, stop choosing, basically, things rooted in aversion, delusion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be impossible for the mind to become, to remain unenlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why if you do four satipaṭṭhānas,
[SPEAKER_01]: As we said, which already means you know what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you already mean you have a right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a one-way only.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would only have to result in what...
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot result in any other way.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I carry on?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I going one-way path?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.